Guide to the Clarina Michelson Papers TAM.240
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Clarina Michelson Papers
Bulk, 1932-1935
1926-1979, (Bulk 1932-1935)
TAM.240
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
Clarina Michelson, the daughter of an affluent and conservative Boston family, was a Communist and labor organizer most active in the 1930s. After attending Radcliff College, she enrolled in the Rand School in New York and joined the Communist Party. She served on the board of the American Fund for Public Service, a foundation that supported labor and radical causes, became a Party organizer in Georgia, played an important role in the Harlem section of the Communist Party and the League of Struggle for Negro Rights, and organized workers for the Department Store Section of the Office Workers Union. The collection contains Communist Party and Communist-led organizations' flyers, leaflets, and internal documents, including meeting notes, clippings, an autobiographical notebook, and an oral history transcript.
Michelson, Clarina, b. 1892
Box 1-3
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Clarina Michelson (b. April 22,1892) came from an affluent, conservative Boston family, and attended Radcliffe College. She moved to New York City, where she attended the Socialist Party's Rand School, then later joined the Communist Party, becoming a long-time activist and sometime cadre. Michelson served (1927-1933) on the board of the American Fund for Public Service, a foundation that supported labor and radical causes. In 1932 she was an Atlanta, Georgia-based Party organizer, working on the 1932 electoral campaign, and on labor and civil rights issues, including the Scottsboro case. Returning to New York, she played an important role in the Harlem section of the Communist Party, and in the League of Struggle for Negro Rights (1932-1934). In 1935 Michelson organized workers for the Department Store Section of the Office Workers Union (affiliated with the Trade Union Unity League), and for the remainder of the decade continued to work in this area after the dissolution of the TUUL. Michelson may have been a Communist Party section organizer in the 1930s and 1940s. In 1979, she was interviewed for the Tamiment Library's Oral History of the American Left Project.
Scope and Content Note
Arranged alphabetically. This small collection contains a valuable selection of Communist Party and Communist-led organizations' flyers, leaflets, and internal documents, including meeting notes, political analysis and reportage by Michelson, as well as clippings, an oral history transcript and a fragmentary autobiographical notebook (both) from her later years. There is an extensive although incomplete set of minutes (1927-1933) of the American Fund for Public Service, and a related file on the Brookwood School (funded in part by the AFPS) concerning the dispute between A.J. Muste and others re the future of the school. The bulk of the material is from the years 1932-1935, and documents Communist Party activities and initiatives, and to a somewhat lesser extent, Michelson's role therein.
Folders for several Southern states (Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky and Tennessee) document the Party's 1932 electoral campaign and anti-lynching and other civil rights struggles, and also some mining and textile organizing activity. Three folders cover New York based Scottsboro case activities of the International Labor Defense's Harlem branch and the Party. Other Harlem-centered activity is documented in folders titled Bus Workers (a campaign to obtain jobs from the Fifth Avenue Coach Company), and League of Struggle for Negro Rights (includes minutes of the League and of the Communist fraction therein). Communist Party materials include Harlem Section notes by Michelson, a folder covering the 1946 anti-Browder campaign in the Lower West Side Club, Michelson's notes from the New York County's Leadership Training School, and a Section Headquarters list for New York State. The Department Store Section of the Office Workers Union is represented by brief files (all from 1935) on various stores, which include issues of short-lived shop papers, and there is also a file on a strike it led at the Jewish Morning Journal. The oral history transcript is of a 1979 interview with Michelson (principally) and several other activists, which chiefly concerns the organizing of department store workers.
The Unemployed folder contains documents from a variety of mass and labor organizations, and exemplifies a research strength of this collection, namely its documentation of the Communist Party's late "Third Period" and the beginning of its transition to a Popular Front orientation (see also the folder on the Joint Unity Committee of Independent Trade Unions). The Teachers Union folder includes several mimeographed issues of the Teacher News, and one issue of the Teachers Union Substitute News. The International Ladies Garment Workers Union Education Department file contains several training documents of left-wing orientation. Finally, there are brief files titled/re: American Labor Party NYC Elections (1946), Children, Radical Leaflets, Women (Communist documents), and the Workers School (NY).
Arrangement
The files are grouped into 1 series.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Clarina Michelson oral history interview (one audiocassette), October 29, 1979, in the Oral History of the American Left Collection, Series I. (A copy of the transcript is in the Michelson Papers.)
Department Store Strikes and Organizing Papers (1930-1941, 5 linear inches). Tamiment Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Tamiment Library does not have information about who donated this collection. The accession number associated with this gift is 1950.082.
American Fund for Public Service.; Communist Party of the United States of America.; International Labor Defense.; League of Struggle for Negro Rights (U.S.).; Michelson, Clarina, b. 1892; Trade Union Unity League (U.S.).; Clerks (Retail trade) |x Labor unions.; Clippings (information artifacts); Communist parties |z United States.; Communist party work.; Communists |z United States.; Documents.; Fliers (printed matter); Labor unions |x Organizing |z United States.; Labor unions |x Political activity |z United States.; Leaflets (printed works); Minutes.; Notebooks.; Scottsboro Trial, Scottsboro, Ala., 1931.; Teachers' unions.
- Container list
  - Alabama, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Fund for Public Service (aka Garland Fund), 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Labor Party, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
  - American League Against War and Fascism, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brookwood Labor College (A.J. Muste conflict), Feb 1933-Mar 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bus Workers / League of Struggle for Negro Rights (NYC), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Children, ca.1933 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Communist Party - - Boro Hall Section (Brooklyn), 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Communist Party District 2 (NY) Agitprop Dept., Other, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Communist Party Harlem Section (NYC) - (see also: box 2, folder 13), 1932-1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Communist Party Lower West Side Section (NYC), 1946 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Communist Party - New York State - Education Department Publications, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10A)
  - Communist Party - New York State - Section Headquarters (list of), undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Florida, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Georgia, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - International Labor Defense, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Labor Defense Harlem Section, 1933-1936 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - International Ladies Garment Workers Union - Education Department, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Morning Journal - office workers strike, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Joint Unity Committee of Independent Trade Unions, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kentucky, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Labor Injunections, 1932, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Labor Research Association - "Why the Wagner Labor Disputes Bill is Anti-Labor", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Leaflets - miscellaneous, ca.1935-1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - League of Struggle for Negro Rights, 1932-1935 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Autobiographical Notebook, ca.1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Michelson, Clarina: College Notebook (Experimental Psychology?), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Michelson, Clarina: "For Comrades Ford and Krumbein" re Harlem Communist Party, 8 p. (see also: box 1, folder 9), Jun 1, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Michelson, Clarina: "Looking Forward in 1935" (a report on the work of the Committee to Support Southern Textile Organization), 3 pp., Jan 2, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Meeting Notes, Lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Michelson, Clarina: "Negro Work", 1934-1935 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Notes - Communist Party New York County Leadership School, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2A)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Oral History Interview Transcript (Audiocassette is in the Oral History of the American Left Collection, Series I.), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Passport, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Michelson, Clarina: Political Writings and Notes, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - National Miners Union, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Office Workers Union, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Office Workers Union: A & S (Abraham & Strauss), 1935 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Office Workers Union: Hearn's, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Office Workers Union: Lerner's, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Office Workers Union: Macy's, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Office Workers Union: "Negro Work", 1935 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Office Workers Union: Orbach's & Klein, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Progressive Citizens of America - Greenwich Village (NYC), 1946 (Box 3, Folder 13A)
  - Scottsboro, 1932-1934 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Scottsboro: Communist Party Agitprop Dept., 1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Southern Organizing, 1931-1932 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Teachers Union, 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Tennessee, ca.1932 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Tennessee: Communist Party Electoral Campaign, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Unemployed, ca.1932-1935 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Women: Communist documents, ca.1933-1935 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Workers School, 1926, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 22)